John Daniel McMahon Papers
John Daniel McMahon Papers
1880-1934
McMahon, John Daniel.
0.5 linear ft.
Incoming and outgoing correspondence with New York State lawyer, politican and legislator John Daniel McMahon. Much of it concerns Democratic Party politics and activities.
4041746
Biographical History
John Daniel McMahon (1859-1923) was an American lawyer, politican and legislator. Born in Toronto, Canada, his family relocated to Annsville, New York in 1861. He attended the Rome Free Academy, read law in the offices of Johnson & Prescott in Rome, and was admitted to the bar in October 1882. In addition to a long and respected legal career, McMahon also for "a period of forty years...held his hand steadily on the democratic party organization of Oneida County, and there was no man in Rome, Utica or elsewhere in the county who...occupied a more commanding position in part affairs." He served as city attorney, city judge and deputy attorney-general; was a delegate to all but two state conventions after 1888 and in frequent demand as an orator on behalf of candidates and the party; and ran for Congress. According to contemporary reports he was popular and widely respected politically, professionally and personally.
[Biographical sketch adapted from Mohawk Valley: Gateway to the West (1925), Nelson Greene, ed., pp.184-189.]
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The John Daniel McMahon Papers consists primarily of correspondence, with a small amount of printed material.
Correspondence consists primarily of incoming correspondence (there are a few items of outgoing) with New York State lawyer, politican and legislator John Daniel McMahon. Much of it concerns Democratic Party politics and activities. Correspondents include Samuel A. Beardsley, democratic leader in Utica; John Carlisle, member of the party's Executive Committee; John Dunham, Utica State Hospital (McMahon was on the Board of Managers); James H. Flanagan, Oneida County politician and businessman; J. F. Gaffney, a fellow judge; James (Jim) Hagarty, New York State Office of Factory Inspectors; D. E. Powers, another attorney; and others.
Financial material contains miscellaneous invoices, etc.
Legal papers contains miscellaneous mortages, rent agreements, depositions, etc.
Printed material contains several items from the Democratic National Convention of 1892, including "A Message From The South!" from the state of Alabama asking Grover Cleveland to decline the nomination, and a large poster announcing the Memorial Day festivities for the town or Oriskany Falls, including the fact that "Hon. J. D. McMahon of Rome, N.Y., will deliver the memorial address."
Arrangement of the Collection
Alphabetical by correspondent.
Related Material
See also the
James H. Flanagan Papers
.
Subject and Genre Headings
New York State; Politics, government and public administration; Beardsley, Samuel, 1790-1860.; Flanagan, James H., Jr.; McMahon, John Daniel.; Wiggins, Howard C.; Williams, E. Stuart.; Democratic Party (N.Y.); New York (State) -- Politics and government -- 1865-1950.; Utica (N.Y.) -- Politics and government -- 1865-1950.; Broadsides (notices); Correspondence.; Legal documents.; Lawyers.; Politicians.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Purchase, 2013, 2015.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - A, miscellaneous, 1891-1893 (Box 1)
  - Barnum, D. A., 1891 (Box 1)
  - Beardsley, Samuel A., 1891 (Box 1)
  - B, miscellaneous, 1887-1912 (gaps) (Box 1)
  - Carlisle, John N., 1891 (Box 1)
  - C, miscellaneous, 1883; 1889-1900 (Box 1)
  - DeFreest, Charles L., 1891 (Box 1)
  - Dempsey, James L., 1891 (Box 1)
  - Dunham, George E., 1891 (Box 1)
  - D, miscellaneous, 1891-1893 (Box 1)
  - E-F, miscellaneous, 1887; 1891,; 1913 (Box 1)
  - Flanagan, James H., 1891 (Box 1)
  - Gaffney, J. F., 1891 (Box 1)
  - G, miscellaneous, 1889; 1891 (Box 1)
  - Hagarty [Heagarty], James, 1891 (Box 1)
  - Hill, David B., 1891 (Box 1)
  - H, miscellaneous, 1891; one item appears to be dated 1881, but it may be an error (Box 1)
  - J-K-L, miscellaneous, 1891-1893 (Box 1)
  - Mason, John E., 1891 (Box 1)
  - McMahon, Mrs. J. D., 1891; 1900-1903 (Box 1)
  - M, miscellaneous, 1884; 1891-1893 (Box 1)
  - N-O, miscellaneous, 1890-1891; 1893 (Box 1)
  - Patten, Harry S., 1891 (Box 1)
  - Powers, D. E., 1891 (Box 1)
  - P, miscellaneous, 1888; 1891,; 1893 (Box 1)
  - R, misc, 1887; 1893,; 1900,; 1902 (Box 1)
  - S-V, 1891; 1893 (Box 1)
  - Wiggins, Howard C., 1893 (Box 1)
  - Williams, E. Stuart, 1891-1893 (Box 1)
  - W, misc, 1891; 1893,; 1898,; 1899 (Box 1)
  - Unidentified (Box 1)
- Financial material
  - Invoices, 1880-1934 (with gaps) (Box 1)
- Legal papers
  - Miscellaneous, 1880; 1885,; 1887,; 1894 (Box 1)
- Printed material
  - Miscellaneous, 1891-1892; Democratic National Convention items; Memorial Day poster (Box 1)